Dr. rer. nat. Martin Bies

Curriculum Vitae



RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau
Department of Mathematics
Gottlieb-Daimler-Straße 48 (Office 433)
67663 Kaiserslautern, Germany
December 15, 1987 (Merzig, Germany)
Single (Not Married)
+49 (0)631 205 2850
martin.bies@rptu.de
https://martinbies.github.io/

German
Native
English
Full Proficiency
French
Modest (CEFR Level B1)

SUMMARY

I hold a **PhD in Physics** (*Heidelberg Univ.*, 2018), specializing in **string theory** and **mathematics**. My research is inspired by **computational analysis** of **massless spectra in string vacua**, resulting in publications on **toric geometry**, **Freyd categories**, **Brill-Noether theory**, and **root bundles**. Proficient in *julia*, C++, and *python*, I excel in **open-source software development** (*git*) to advance **computational research**. My diverse expertise emphasizes my interdisciplinary commitment. With a history of **international collaborations**, full **English proficiency**, and extensive **teaching experience**, I showcase a versatile skill set.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

CURRENT, FROM IO/2022 (FT)

Mathematics Dept., RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau, GER *Research Associate*

I enhance the toric geometry capabilities and develop advanced algebraic geometry tools for string theory geometries within the OSCAR computer algebra system (oscar-system.org). Funded by the SFB-TRR 195 – Symbolic Tools in Mathematics and their Application and the Forschungsinitiative des Landes Rheinland-Pfalz, I added/modified 160,000+ lines of code.

09/202I - 08/2022 (FT)

Dept. of Phys. & Astron., University of Pennsylvania, USA *Simons Postdoctoral Fellow*

Continuation of Simons Foundation project, detailed below.

09/2020 - 08/202I (FT)

Dept. of Mathematics, University of Pennsylvania, USA Simons Postdoctoral Fellow

Work with M. Cvetič and R. Donagi on root bundles and the F-theory QSMs (funded by the *Simons Foundation*).

10/2019 - 09/2020 (FT)

Mathematical Institute, University of Oxford, UK Long Term Visitor

Continuation of Wiener-Anspach project initiated at PTM, Brussels.

10/2018 - 09/2019 (FT)

PTM, Université Libre de Bruxelles, BE

Postdoctoral Researcher

M/F-Theory: Engineering Of Super Conformal Field Theories (funded by the *Foundation Wiener-Anspach*).

ITP, Heidelberg University, GER

Research Associate

AI-tools meet jumps in vector-like spectra (preparation of Cluster of Excellence EXC 2181 STRUCTURES).

EDUCATION

03/2014 - 02/2018 PhD in Physics (Grade: Magna Cum Laude)

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND (PHYSICS) & PROF. M. BARAKAT (MATHEMATICS)

Heidelberg University, GER

09/2012 - 02/2014 Master of Physics (Grade: 1.0)

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND
Heidelberg University, GER

10/2010 - 06/2011 ERASMUS exchange student

Imperial College, London

10/2008 - 08/2012 **Bachelor of Physics (Grade: 1.1)**

ADVISOR: PROF. T. WEIGAND Heidelberg University, GER

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

04/2024 - CURRENT TU-Nachwuchsring

Status: M. Mikelsons (B.Sc. Mathematics) hired as research assistant.

Goal: Enhance the OSCAR computer algebra system (oscar-system.org),

focusing on the FTheoryTools module, and utilize it for research.

01/2010 - 02/2018 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes

2015: Awarded PhD scholarship.

2010: Awarded Bachelor and Master scholarship.

10/2010 – 06/2011 ERASMUS scholarship

SERVICES

07/2024 Organizer of session at conference *ICMS 2024* (together with M. Zach & L. Kastner).

02/2024 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board (virtual event).

FALL 2023 & 2024 Expert at European Commission for accessment of research proposals.

SINCE 2021 10+ letters of recommendation.

06/2018 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board *Heidelberg*.

12/2017 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Ellwangen III.

11/2016 Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes: Member of the admission board Heidelberg.

PUBLICATIONS

```
0000-0002-9609-1693
                   ORCID
                           57197835420
                 SCOPUS
                           5 (Based on peer-reviewed works, only.)
                H-INDEX
    TOTAL PUBLICATIONS
PEER REVIEWED/ACCEPTED
          UNDER REVIEW
              OUTREACH
           UNPUBLISHED
                  THESIS
              JOUR NALS
                          Journal of High Energy Physics (5)
                           Journal of Algebra and Its Applications (1)
                           Physical Review D (1)
                           Proceedings of Symposia in Pure Mathematics (AMS) (1)
                           Communications In Mathematical Physics (1)
```

Peer Reviewed Publications

- I M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, Improved Statistics for F-theory Standard Models, Communications in Mathematical Physics, Nov. 2024, DOI: 10.1007/s00220-024-05148-7.
- M. Bies, Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models, in String-Math 2022, R. Donagi, A. Langer, P. Sułkowski, and K. Wendland, eds., Proceedings of Symposia in Pure Mathematics, vol. 107, American Mathematical Society, 2024, pp. 17–43. ISBN: 978-1-4704-7240-5. DOI: 10.1090/pspum/107. (A preprint is available at arXiv:2303.08144.)
- 3 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Ong, Brill-Noether-general Limit Root Bundles: Absence of vector-like Exotics in F-theory Standard Models, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2022, DOI: 10.1007/JHEPII(2022)004.
- 4 **M. Bies**, M. Cvetič, M. Liu, *Statistics of Root Bundles Relevant for Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs*, Physical Review D, Sept. 2021, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.104.L061903.
- 5 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, M. Liu, M. Ong, Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of Ftheory MSSMs, Journal of High Energy Physics, Sept. 2021, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP09(2021)076
- 6 M. Bies, S. Posur, *Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors*, Journal of Algebra and Its Applications, July. 2021, DOI: 10.1142/s0219498822501869.
- 7 M. Bies, M. Cvetič, R. Donagi, L. Ling, M. Liu, F. Ruehle, *Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, Jan. 2021, DOI: 10.1007/JHEP01(2021)196.
- 8 **M. Bies**, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, *Algebraic Cycles and Local Anomalies in F-theory*, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2017, DOI: 10.1007/jhep11(2017)100.
- 9 M. Bies, C. Mayrhofer, T. Weigand, Gauge Backgrounds and Zero-Mode Counting in F-theory, Journal of High Energy Physics, Nov. 2017, DOI: 10.1007/jhep11(2017)081.

Outreach

- M. Bies, A. P. Turner, *F-Theory Applications*, in *The Computer Algebra System OSCAR: Algorithms and Examples*, W. Decker, C. Eder, C. Fieker, M. Horn, and M. Joswig, eds., Algorithms and Computation in Mathematics, vol. 32, Springer, 1st ed., to appear by end of 2024, pp. 453–475. ISSN: 1431-1550.
- M. Bies, L. Kastner, *Toric Geometry*, in *The Computer Algebra System OSCAR: Algorithms and Examples*, W. Decker, C. Eder, C. Fieker, M. Horn, and M. Joswig, eds., Algorithms and Computation in Mathematics, vol. 32, Springer, 1st ed., to appear by end of 2024, pp. 193–213. ISSN: 1431-1550.
- M. Bies, L. Kastner, *Toric Geometry in OSCAR*, ComputerAlgebraRundbrief 72 (03/2023), 20-25, Mar. 2023, Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08110.

Unpublished Works

13 **M. Bies**, C. Mayrhofer, C. Pehle, T. Weigand, *Chow Groups, Deligne Cohomology and Massless Matter in F-theory*, Feb. 2014, https://arxiv.org/abs/1402.5144.

Thesis

- M. Bies, Cohomologies of Coherent Sheaves and Massless Spectra in F-theory, PhD thesis, Heidelberg university, Feb. 2018, Heidelberg University Library, available at DOI: 10.11588/HEIDOK.00024045.
- 15 **M. Bies**, Cohomologies of holomorphic line bundles in smooth and compact normal toric varieties, M.Sc. thesis, Heidelberg university, February 2014, available on author's academic homepage.
- 16 **M. Bies**, Intersecting D6-brane models on $T^2 \times T^2 \times T^2 / (\sigma \times \Omega)$ and $T^2 \times T^2 \times T^2 / (\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2 \times \sigma \times \Omega)$ orientifolds, B.Sc. thesis, Heidelberg university, August 2012, available on author's academic homepage.

TEACHING RECORD

Autonomous Instruction of Lecture Courses

Period	Title	University	Students	Weekly Teaching	Evaluation
04/2024 - 07/2024	Introduction to Topology	RPTU KL-LD, GER	5	1×1.5 hours	Insufficient data due to sharp drop in RPTU KL-LD student numbers.
0I/2022 - 05/2022	Computational Linear Algebra	University Of Pennsylvania, USA	29	$2 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$	2.12
01/2021 - 05/2021	Computational Linear Algebra	University Of Pennsylvania, USA	57	$2 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$	2.04

Scale: Poor (0), Fair (1), Good (2), Very good (3), Excellent (4).

Senior Teaching Assistant

Period	Title	University	Students	Weekly Teaching
10/2023 – current	Algebraic Geometry	RPTU KL-LD, GER	6	1×1.5 hours
04/2018 - 10/2018	Methods of Math. Phys.	Heidelberg University, GER	51	1×1.5 hours
04/2016 - 09/2016	General Relativity	Heidelberg University, GER	132	$1 \times 1.5 \mathrm{hours}$

Teaching Assistant

Period	Title	University	Weekly Teaching
10/2016 - 03/2017	Theoretical Physics I	Heidelberg University, GER	1×1.5 hours
04/2015 - 09/2015	Theoretical Physics IV	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5 \text{hours}$
10/2014 - 03/2015	Quantum Field Theory	Heidelberg University, GER	1×1.5 hours
10/2013 - 03/2014	Theoretical Physics III	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5 \text{hours}$
04/2013 - 09/2013	Theoretical Physics II	Heidelberg University, GER	1×1.5 hours
10/2012 - 03/2013	Theoretical Physics I	Heidelberg University, GER	$1 \times 1.5 \text{ hours}$

TALKS, POSTERS, CONFERENCES

Organizer of Conference (1)

07/2024 Session at ICMS 2024 (Durham, UK)

Invited Talks (8)

- o7/2023 Third Annual Meeting 2023 of SFB-TRR 195 (Saarbruecken, GER)
 Title: F-Theory: Exemplifying OSCAR's Pursuit for Multidisciplinary Excellence
- 05/2023 Oberseminar algebraische Geometrie (Saarbruecken, GER) Title: F-Theory and Singular Elliptic Fibrations
- 10/2020 Philadelphia, USA
 Title: Machine Learning and Algebraic Approaches towards Complete Matter Spectra in 4d F-theory
- o6/2020 Summer Series on String Phenomenology (Virtual)
 Title: On Stratification Diagrams, Algorithmic Spectrum Estimates and Vector-Like Pairs in F-theory
- 12/2019 Philadelphia, USA Title: From F-theory Standard Models to Freyd Categories and back
- 10/2018 Brussels, BE
 Title: Counting Massless Matter in F-theory with CAP
- 08/2018 *CAP_days 2018* (Siegen, GER)
 Title: CAP, *Machine Learning and String Theory*
- o7/2014 Aachen, GER
 Title: The Standard Model from String Theory

Other Talks at Conferences, Workshops etc. (15)

- o6/2024 StringPheno 2024 (Pardova, IT)
 Title: Efficiency in F-Theory: FTheoryTools
- o7/2023 StringMath 2023 (Melbourne, AU)
 Title: Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models
- o7/2023 StringPheno 2023 (Daejeon, KR)
 Title: Root bundles: Applications to F-theory Standard Models
- o5/2023 Computeralgebra Tagung 2023 (Hannover, GER)
 Title: F-Theory Tools: String theory Applications of OCSAR
- 07/2022 String Math 2022 (Warsaw, PL) Title: Towards F-theory MSSMs
- 07/2022 String Pheno 2022 (Liverpool, UK) Title: Towards F-theory MSSMs
- 09/2021 Summer Series on String Phenomenology (virtual meeting)
 Title: Root Bundles and Towards Exact Matter Spectra of F-theory MSSMs
- 12/2020 *String Data 2020* (virtual conference)
 Title: *Vector-like spectra in F-theory* (joined with M. Liu)
- 08/2019 Gap Singular Meeting and School (Lambrecht, GER)
 Title: Monoidal Structures in Freyd Categories
- 05/2018 Seminar on *Holography and Large-N duality* (Heidelberg, GER)

Title: Conformal Invariants; Fefferman–Graham Expansion; Graham–Lee Theorem (with M. Zikidis) String Pheno 2017 (Virginia, USA) 07/2017 Title: Zero Mode Counting in F-Theory via CAP GAP Days (Aachen, GER) 08/2014 Title: String Theory, Sheaf Cohomology and the homalg Package Seminar Series What is? (Heidelberg, GER) 05/2014 Title: What is a Fermion/Boson (in Quantum Mechanics)? Heidelberg, GER 02/2014 Title: Cohomology of Holomorphic Pullback Line Bundles on Smooth, Compact Normal Toric Varieties Heidelberg, GER 05/2012 Title: Intersecting D6-Brane Models Posters at Conferences, Workshops etc. (2) StringMath 2023 (Melbourne, AU) 07/2023 Title: FTheoryTools – A Computer Tool for Singular Elliptic Fibrations

Conferences attended without Talk or Poster Contribution (17)

Title: Tensor Products of Finitely Presented Functors

Strings and Geometry (Oxford, UK)

09/2019

02/2014

07/2022 Strings 2022 (Vienna, AT) 06/2022 Simons Collab.: Geometry, Topology and Singular Special Holonomy Spaces (Freiburg, GER) Simons Collab. (Homological Mirror Symmetry) Annual Meeting (New York, USA) 11/2021 Simons Collab.: Progress and Open Problems (Stony Brook, USA) 09/2021 Simons Collab. (Special Holonomy in Geometry, Analysis, Phys.) Annual Meeting (New York, USA) 09/2021 07/2021 String Pheno 2021 (virtual conference) Strings 2021 (virtual conference) 06/2021 String Math 2021 (virtual conference) 06/2021 String Pheno 2020 (virtual conference) 06/2020 Strings 2019 (Brussels, BE) 07/2019 03/2018 String Data 2018 (Munich, GER) 12/2015 String Math 2015 (Sanya, CN) Third GAP Days (Trondheim, NO) 09/2015 Second GAP Days (Aachen, GER) 03/2015 *Physics and Geometry of F-Theory* (Munich, GER) 02/2015 Homological Perturbation Theory (Galway, IE) 12/2014 Geometry and Physics of String Compactifications (Heidelberg, GER)

OTHER TRAININGS

03/2024 Moderation of meetings and project discussions (Kaiserslautern, GER).

Offered by: TU Nachwuchsring

05/2018 Kontaktseminar – Schwerpunkt Banken und Beratung (Bonn, GER)

Offered by: Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes

05/2018 Physiker im Beruf (Bad Honnef, GER)

Offered by: Deutsche Physikalische Gesellschaft (DPG)

05/2017 Training for admission board members (Frankfurt, GER)

Offered by: Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes

REFERENCES

Prof. Dr. Mirjam Cvetič

POSITION Fay R. and Eugene L. Langberg Professor

EMPLOYER Department of Physics and Astronomy

University of Pennsylvania, USA

EMAIL cvetic@physics.upenn.edu

PHONE +1 (215) 898 8153

Prof. Dr. Ron Donagi

POSITION Thomas A. Scott Professor of Mathematics

EMPLOYER Department of Mathematics

University of Pennsylvania, USA

EMAIL donagi@math.upenn.edu

PHONE +1 (215) 898 8465

Prof. Dr. Max Horn

POSITION Professor

EMPLOYER Department of Mathematics

RPTU Kaiserslautern-Landau, GER

EMAIL mhorn@rptu.de PHONE +49 63I 205 2730